A Guide to the Henkel-Miller Family Papers, 1793-1910
University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence of the Henkel Press
  - 1806-1817 George (John George, J.G., Johann Georg) Schmucker to Solomon Henkel (7 items). Hagerstown, Maryland. June 9, 1806: relays a letter from Mr. Helmuth, an author; July 1806: handwritten copy of the "Constitution of our German Book Business"; September 7, 1806: printing business and a reference to John Gruber; November 20, 1807: ABC books; January 6, 1808: business with Ambrose, Andrew and Mr. Schmidt from Lexington; February 1, 1809: pleased to see that Solomon spoke with Mr. Woltz about the books, instructions to Solomon regarding the selling of books, regards to Ambrose; January 21 1813 (York): business, magazines, printing, references to Ambrose and Charles. Letters in German. (Box-folder 2:7)
  - 1805-1811 Congressman John Smith to Solomon Henkel (18 items), Washington City. January 3, 1805: House and Senate business, new territory of Michigan; January 17, 1805: Burr's Trial for killing Hamilton; January 21, 1805: bill for dividing Indiana territory has passed; January 31, 1805: Business in Washington, "Mr. Randolph has shown his violence"; February 15, 1805: Trial of Judge Chase, Dr. Dulaney opposes the delegation of John Smith; December 11, 1806: War in Europe; November 21, 1807: talk of war and Bonaparte; December 20, 1807: trouble with Britain and France; January 30, 1808: Supposition of war; February 23, 1809: embargo; February 11, 1810: preparations for war; January 17, 1811: President's confidential message, closing of [United States?] Bank. Letters in English (Box-folder 2:8)
  - 1827-1829 J.N. Stirewalt to Solomon Henkel (2 items). Abington, Virginia and Lincoln County, North Carolina. Business partner of the Henkels, these letters are travel reports with some business matters. August 31, 1827: details the difficulties of a journey, asks Solomon to relay the details to his mother, viewed Natural Bridge; September 9, 1829: states that some of Solomon's pills helped with a fever, requests a copy of Luther's entire work. Letters in English. (Box-folder 2:9)
  - 1808-1812 L. Trimper to Solomon Henkel (6 items). Staunton, Virginia. Concerns the purchase of books from the Henkel Press. November 4, 1808: request for one dozen Lutheran or church catechisms in German for selling, and four dozen German almanacs as well as English ones; June 13, 1809: there is a German teacher in Staunton but no books, request German spelling and grammar books; May 22, 1811: requests German grammar and ABC books to sell to many men in the area. August 17, 1811: sending money for twelve ABC books and "Sprechen Lehrer" (German language books); April 24, 1812: request for more books. Letters in English. (Box-folder 2:10)
  - 1817-1836 Valley Iron to Solomon Henkel (7 items). Correspondence of various iron works in the Shenandoah Valley, to include: Union Forge, Adam Douglass, Isabella Furnace, Liberty Furnace, and Caroline Furnace. Letters in English. (Box-folder 2:11)
  - 1811-1822 Warner (William) and Schaeffer (F.G.) to Solomon Henkel (11 items). Baltimore, Maryland. A supplier of the Henkels, often sending goods through Henry Keerl & Sons. Letter of note: March 26, 1813: "We have received two boxes from Philadelphia addressed to you. To send you them via Alexandria would expose them to the fangs of the British squadron" asks for alternate means of conveyance. Letters in English (Box-folder 2:12)
  - 1812-1814, n.d. War of 1812 Subject in Letters. (Box-folder 2:13)
    May 8, 1812: Jacob Stiegel to Solomon Henkel, concerns the moral implications of serving one's country; May 23, 1813: John Miller to Solomon Henkel, Informs Henkel that he is now a Lieutenant serving a six month tour at Norfolk; September 9, 1814: Webster Lewis to Solomon Henkel, disrupted business and the defense of Baltimore; September 24, 1814: William Warner to Solomon Henkel, Battle of North Point; November 14, 1814: Martin Harry to Solomon Henkel, conditions at Camp Crossroads (XRodes); n.d.: "A New Song about the Defeat of St. Claire in the Western Territory".
  - 1813-1824, n.d. Laurentz Wartmann to Solomon Henkel (13 items). Harrisonburg, Virginia. Printer/publisher in Rockingham County and editor of the Rockingham Register. April 27, 1813: Apologizes for creating so much work for Solomon, some business about a cow; January 10, 1814: three letters in one, extremely cordial, essentially a "Happy New Year" letter; March 9, 1814: death of Elisabeth, request for one dozen English [ __ ] and two songs; May 16, 1815: Letter of introduction for Mr. Stone; enjoyed the visit, requests Solomon to tell Mrs. Dairy that she must have patience until Mr. Bourne returns from Philadelphia in four weeks; March 26, 1816: book business; July 17, 1816: sends an example of a music book, needs letters (type); August 27, 1816: hopes Solomon is happy with the books, will visit in four weeks; October 2, 1816; must cancel his visit because of money, hopes music books have been bound; January 29, 1817; has received the letters (type) from Mr. Hauck and will send them back to Solomon at the first opportunity; December 1, 1821: currently building a printing press; May 23, 1823: tells Solomon to get a thaler from Philip Knopf to give to John Will and to get a receipt; January 23, 1824: expects paper from Winchester this week, needs to get some from Solomon; September 10 18__: Mr. Davison is disposed to print something, might print and publish in Harrisonburg, needs help from Solomon and will share the profits. Letters in German. (Box-folder 2:14)
  - 1814-1819 Philip Williams to Solomon Henkel (4 items). Woodstock, Virginia. Business and Religious matters. April 15, 1811: requests blank books to be made as soon as possible, legal issues concerning apothecaries; May 21, 1814: legal issues concerning drugs and medicines; May 30, 1814: additional help with legal matters pertaining to the selling of medicine; July 2, 1819: Reverend William Armstrong will preach in New Market and requests notice be given, discussed salary for Armstrong. Letters in English. (Box-folder 2:15)
  - 1807-1811 Jacob Woltz to Solomon Henkel (7 items). Fincastle, Virginia. Purchases various articles from Solomon Henkel. April 21, 1807: medicine received, "waggoner" was paid twice, calls him a 'raskel.'; May 26, 1807: clears up a matter of a transaction, includes additional list of items requested; June 18, 1807: asks Solomon if he has received sent money; August 18, 1807: all things arrived safely, issue of cost; October 5, 1809: requests some medical items to be sent; April 7, 1810: a man had his brains knocked out by the fall of a tree, requests lampblack and verdigris; February 9, 1811: reference to slavery, "have had a busy time of it for some time past with some Negroes that murdered thare masters. We hung five the first day of this month." Asks for a barrel of sugar candy. Letters in English. (Box-folder 2:16)
- Series II: Correspondence of the Henkel Family
  - 1800-1821 Andrew Henkel to Solomon Henkel (20 items). Various locations. 1803 February 13, Family events with a sketch of flowers; June 10, 1810: "Are you all dead? Or are you sleeping," has received no response to all his letters, request for English song books; August 8, 1811: has sent as much money as he has received; September, 1811: was at a conference the Monday prior where Mr. Miller told him that Mr. Dreher wants five hundred English catechisms; September 7, 1811: Philip arrived last night from the city, horse is sick (the old Gaul), short poem at the end; July 7, 1812: will remain in Point Pleasant for the time being, trying to get some items sent; January 31, 1813: has received the letter from Paul forwarded by Solomon, pleased to hear that the press will stay in New Market; November 12, 1813: departs by boat to the land Kugert bought, believes a German school here would be a greater advantage than preaching itself; November 15, 1813: believes that a lot of books can be sold in Ohio; June 23, 1814: reference to Heinrich Zerkel, staying with the brothers-in-law of Kugert, wants to visit next winter; July 12, 1814: Kugert and Mammi (Nanni) are sick, set up a children's school; August 15, 1814: Nanni has been very sick for 6 weeks, but not consistently, preaching and teaching; March 28, 1816: preached sixteen times in four weeks; April 19, 1817: writing a fourth time in hopes of an answer, has received a letter from father (Paul), preaching, it is 11AM and he is fourteen miles away from where he wants to be in the afternoon; April 11, 1818: Cannot help it if father moans about him, most of the books are sold; December 19, 1818: Money matters (owes Solomon), printing matters, but primarily details of all his business matters and how he will get the money to Solomon; January 20, 1820: has not written in a while, sold a house, thanks Solomon for the money, church business; Letters in German and English. (Box-folder 2:17)
  - 1793-1825, n.d. Paul Henkel to Solomon and Ambrose Henkel (23 items). Various locations. November 26, 1803: Wythe County, Virginia, business with George and Carl Greim, itinerant activities in Virginia, preaching several places by name; May 7, 1804: [Margintown ?] (not entirely at the end of the world), reference to Mr. Jacob Scharrer, he is 110 miles from home, itinerate preaching, reference to Laros; May 10, 1804: Philip's progress in the office of Preacher, includes a watercolor by the young Andrew Henkel; February 23, 1805: has had the hardest winter, family news, a great abundance of blacks in Charleston; January 12, 1812: need for an English catechism, the ones he has are all in use for the instruction of youth, Mr. John Hofmann has begun a German school; February 7, 1812: selling of books, earthquake; February 12, 1812: "almost impossible this Winter to write something proper," North Carolina needs more hymn books and Ohio want more as well, refers to letter of January 12 where he states that he has not done (or received) an English catechism, yet now there has been a mention of requests for English hymn books; February 13, 1812: reference to 1805, Stocks County, North Carolina, via some verse, printing matters; March 15, 1812: today he preaches in the house of Daniel Rausch in German and English, tomorrow he has to educate the youth 18 miles away, reference to Laros (reformed preacher); April 6, 1812: concerns educational books, Mrs. Sterrit, invitation to visit in May; August 4, 1812: arrived in Harrisburg yesterday evening, business with a Mr. Sufren; December 8, 1812: mentions a print shop in Lincoln, North Carolina, reference to conference, wants to allow to be published the accomplishments of the North Carolina conference in Lincoln; 1812: he is on his trip to Richmond; September 23, 1821: from the house of Caspar Reinard, will be staying the night with the church of a Mr. Schlager, reference to General Synod, Bluntsville, Sulivin (Sullivan) County, postscript in a different hand says they were in Fairfield with Mr. Albrecht; November 23, 1825: Death announcement of Paul Henkel; n.d.: genealogy of Paul Henkel and his descendants. Letters in German. (Box-folder 2:18)
  - 1800-1811 Philip Henkel-Various Correspondence (4 items). Martinsburg, Virginia and Lincolnton, North Carolina. February 3, 1807: received the handbill, settled in Lincolnton and has a house and lots; January 31, 1810: relays news about the Lorntz and Milli (Miller?) families, people think that Old Man Milli left a wife and son in Switzerland, possibility of selling land to a neighbor (Motz), genealogical notes on himself and his family; November 5, 1811: evangelistic and personal matters; Letters in German. (Box-folder 2:19)
  - 1825-1854, n.d. Correspondence of Samuel G. Henkel (23 items). Various locations. Correspondence to and from Samuel G. Henkel. Correspondents include:, William A. Evans (Columbus, Mississippi), [K] Krauth (Gettysburg, Pennsylvania), the Rev. J.G. Morris (Baltimore, Maryland), William M. Reynolds (Colubus, Ohio), Jacob Savage (Wayne County, Indiana), H.J. Schmidt (New York), and C. Spielmann (Columbus, Ohio). September 11, 1825: Samuel G. Henkel to Solomon Henkel: has arrived in Winchester Uncle Abraham will come in a few weeks from Baltimore, prices of goods in Winchester, observations on a church and minister there; August 10, 1832, William A. Evans to Samuel G. Henkel: medical practice, description of Lowdes County, cholera and President Jackson "who is almost idolized in this part of the country."; January 27, 1833, Samuel G. Henkel to Solomon Henkel: shipping of a cupboard and other unspecified articles; March 13, 1843, L. Salyards to Henkel Press: praises the village of New Market, applies for job at the academy; January 6, 1844, Jacob Savage to Samuel G. Henkel: request for money and medical advice; May 14, 1844, Jacob Savage to Samuel G. Henkel: death of Silon (Solon?, Silas?) A. Henkel; April 20, 1849, Jacob Savage to Samuel G. Henkel: domestic matters, request for a loan; July 10, 1849, Jacob Savage to Samuel G. Henkel: money matters, continuation of business from April 20 letter, November 3, 1851, C. Spielmann to Samuel G. Henkel: concerns the publication of a manuscript; December 15, 1851, C. Spielmann to Samuel G. Henkel: has mailed the manuscript of Salyard's article referred to in November 3 letter, notes on the revision of a theological book; May 28, 1852, William M. Reynolds to Henkel Press: has carefully revised his portion of the Book of Concord, notes concerning it; November 5, 1852, Krauth to Samuel G. Henkel: refers to Drs. [Charles N.] Schaeffer and Schmidt as gentlemen who can help with revisions; July 24 and 27, 1853, Rev. J.G. Morris to Samuel G. Henkel: translation of the Concordien Buch is finished; November 21, 1854, H.J. Schmidt to Solomon D. Henkel (who is deceased) and Bros: has received a copy of the Concordien Buch; n.d., Jacob Savage to Samuel G. Henkel: cholera in the area, people dying fast. Letters in English and German. (Box-folder 2:20)
  - 1824-1825 Sylvanus Henkel to Samuel G. Henkel (3 items). Sommerset, Ohio and New Market, Virginia. Letters account of his journey to Ohio: mileage, cost, etc. References to Uncles David, Andrew (Andreas) and Charles (Carolus), Herr Riemenschneider. November 19, 1825 notes that Grandfather (Paul Henkel) is very sick. Letters in German. (Box-folder 2:21)
  - 1799-1857 Correspondence of the Henkel Family (12 items). Various locations. Correspondents include: Gideon Henkel, Moses Henkel, Jacob Henkel, Charles (Carolus) Henkel, Ambrose Henkel, David Henkel, William M. Reynolds, and Sarah C. Ayer. Letter of note: June 30, 1857, Sarah C. Ayer to Rebecca M. Henkel: she is teaching and will remain in Warrenton because the school is good, German is becoming "quite fashionable now." Letters in German and English. (Box-folder 2:22)
  - 1815-1910, n.d. Henkel Press Business Items (12 items). Includes accounts and shipping orders with various clients. Letters in German and English. (Box-folder 3:1)
  - 1804-1848, n.d. Legal Documents (18 items). Items include: Saul Henkel's appointment to Lieutenant in the militia, debt notes of John Bury (New Market cabinet maker), an original manuscript for the printing of an advertisement broadside for selling a carding machine by Strasburg merchants, an indenture between James and Ann Booker and John Savage, an Article of Agreement between John Savage and Samuel G. Henkel, a Note of Agreement of John Savage, an Indenture between James and Ann Booker and Ambrose Henkel, and Article of Agreement between Solomon Henkel and Christian Whitmire (miller at Plains Mill), a boarding agreement for Rachel Deary, a draft of an address delivered to the Imitative Legislature by Samuel G. Henkel, a fine on Samuel G. Henkel for nonattendance at muster, a lawsuit of Ambrose Henkel et.al. against George Goodman et.al., and specifications of Summer's Dam to be built next to the land of John Savage. (Box-folder 3:2)
  - n.d. "Second Journey of Dr. Solomon Henkel to Philadelphia." Transcription in a later hand with added notes. Contains references to traveling as well as to family members and acquaintances. Letters in English. (Box-folder 3:3)
  - n.d. Historical Notes on the Henkel Family (7 items). "Family Record of Samuel Godfrey Henkel"; "A Journey to Philadelphia over a Century Ago" notes on a diary of Solomon Henkel in a later hand; a timeline and a list of books printed in New Market by Ambrose Henkel's office (also in a later hand). Draft article entitled "The Comstock Lode" for the Shenandoah Valley Folklore Society newsletter. Letters in English. (Box-folder 3:4)
  - n.d. "Sons of Rev. Paul Henkel" - Pictures. Photographs, or photographs of paintings of, Solomon, Ambrose and Andrew Henkel, Drawing of David Henkel, Silhouette of Philip Henkel. (5 3:5)
  - n.d. Marbling Paper. Sample used for books from the Henkel Press. (Box-folder 3:6)
  - c.1890 Photograph of Original Henkel Press Building in New Market, Virginia. (Box-folder 3:7)
  - n.d. Photograph of Solomon Henkel (or of a painting of him) (Box-folder 3:8)
  - n.d. Booklet Written to Ambrose Henkel [by Solomon] on Lutheranism. German. (Box-folder 3:9)
  - 1850-1862 Album of Gems-owned by Julia Henkel. A memento book containing poems, keepsakes, and entries written by friends addressed to "Ginnie." One entry states: "This leaf was sent to me by my brother Caspar, whilst on picket near Fredericksburg, on the Rappahannock. December 26th, 1862." Letters in English. (Box-folder 3:10)
  - 1799 Travel Diary and Religious Notes of Paul Henkel. German. (Box-folder 3:11)
  - 1804-1806, 1814 Day Book of Paul Henkel. German. (Box-folder 3:12)
  - 1811-1816 Personal Diary of Paul Henkel. Contains brief daily entries as well as birth records. German. (Box-folder 3:13)
  - n.d. Memoranda Travel Book of Paul Henkel. Records many Valley births in 1782-3 as well as a contract for bonding and some German-Latin vocabulary. (Box-folder 3:14)
  - n.d. Devotional Booklet of Paul Henkel. German. (Box-folder 3:15)
  - n.d. Notebook of Philip Henkel. Records a trip. German. (Box-folder 4:1)
  - 1823 April 3 Samuel G. Henkel's Book of Biblical Verses (Box-folder 4:2)
  - 1826 April Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum Book. English (Box-folder 4:3)
  - 1828 April Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum Book. English (Box-folder 4:4)
  - 1828 October Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum Book. Includes a sketch of the bridge at Harpers Ferry. English. (Box-folder 4:5)
  - 1829 April Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum Book. English and German. (Box-folder 4:6)
  - 1829 October Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum Book. English.s (Box-folder 4:7)
  - 1829 October Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum Book. English. (Box-folder 4:8)
  - 1831 October 14 Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum Book. English. (Box-folder 4:9)
  - 1849-1851 Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum Book. English. (Box-folder 4:10)
  - 1852-1856 Samuel G. Henkel's Memorandum Book. English. (Box-folder 4:11)
  - 1833 April 8 Siram P. Henkel's Memorandum Book (Box-folder 5:1)
  - 1845 Day Book of Socrates Henkel. English. (Box-folder 5:2)
  - n.d. Personal Booklet of a Henkel Family Member with a French-German Learning Device (Box-folder 5:3)
  - 1823 Notebook of Joseph S. Rupert (Box-folder 5:4)
  - 1829 "Memorandum of Books, etc. Placed in the Care of Several Agents in N.C. and Tennessee." (Box-folder 5:5)
  - 1839 Memorandum Book (Box-folder 5:6)
- Series III: Manuscripts Intended for Publication
  - n.d. Manuscript-"Bedenken über den Thorheit der Menschen" (Box-folder 5:7)
  - 1805 September 4 [Manuscript]-"Ein Christags Geschenk für Kinder die im neuen Testemente lesen über das sogenannte Christkindlein"-by Paul Henkel (Box-folder 5:8)
  - n.d. [Manuscript]-Church Hymn Book 2nd Ed.-by Paul Henkel (Box-folder 5:9)
  - n.d. Manuscript- Kurzer Anzug der Teologiae (Box-folder 5:10)
  - n.d. [Manuscript]-Latin-German Study Book written by Solomon Henkel (Box-folder 5:11)
  - n.d. Manuscript-"Ein Memorial an die ehrw. Lutherische Synode von Märeland und Virginia." (Box-folder 5:12)
  - 1805 [Manuscript]-"Negro Song"-made by Saul Henkel (Box-folder 5:13)
  - c. 1817 [Manuscript]-"Proceedings of a Special Conference Held in Madison County" (Box-folder 5:14)
  - n.d. Religious Manuscripts meant for Publication, 3 items (Box-folder 5:15)
  - n.d. Science and Medicine Manuscripts - Possibly for Publication, 2 items (Box-folder 5:16)
  - 1823Tieren Büch-Samuel G. Henkel (Box-folder 5:17)
  - 1823 Accompanying Illustrations for Tieren Büch (Box-folder 5:18)
  - n.d. Vocabulary Book (Box-folder 5:19)